Oh, you're allergic to us, George? Nasty.
>> Yeah.
How are you doing? Nothing until I turned on audio either.
I know. You're allergic to us. Yeah.
Something like that.
Okay.
Almost time to go.
Hi, guys.
Hi.
Hello.
Hello. Glo.
Evening, George. Hi, Joy. How are doing?
Not too bad.
Good. Little warmer.
>> Any,
yeah, right. Any any freeze ups that you had to deal with or anything?
No. Go ahead.
No.
Uncommonly
>> cold. Yeah. Nothing that a little salt on. Yeah,
nothing that a little salt on the edge of the road couldn't handle.
You about ready, George?
Beg pardon?
Are you about
ready?
>> Yeah, right. It is now. Well, I'm just waiting for it to hit 07:00 on my computer. Very good.
Give everybody a chance to show up.
Okay.
Okay, it's now 7PM
on
Monday, 02/06/2023.
I will call to order this regular meeting of the Andover Inland Wetlands and Water Courses Commission.
I see on the call
Commissioners Larson,
Maske,
and Monroe.
Not present
would be
Commissioner Smith.
Are there any
suggestions for changes or additions to the agenda?
I have none, and
seeing nothing from Commissioners,
we'll proceed then to Item Number four of the agenda,
approval of the minutes of 01/10/2023.
Again, I trust everybody's had a chance to
peruse those minutes and
ask them for
corrections
or
suggested
modifications
of the minutes?
I do have a correction.
Commissioner Monroe, yes.
My
last name is misspelled.
Okay,
well,
I certainly don't want that.
And
>> I'll I'll take care of that for you. Yeah. It's with a u, m u. Everybody Okay. Common.
Okay.
Anything else?
Commissioner Larson.
I'm all set.
>> Commissioner Maski.
Looks good.
Okay.
I had a couple of comments,
mostly really not to the substance but to the
grammar expression.
And
let's see, let me pull this up.
When we get down to
item, well, first of all, item number one,
the minutes state that I called to order a public hearing, actually it was a meeting,
okay?
So, I'll make that distinction
correction.
And then
when we get into
item number 9A,
it's a little muddled,
and I think we want to say I'm
going to suggest some corrections,
which I will
forward to the clerk for purpose
of clarity,
but let me mention them in
this context.
The
sense number two, I would say rather than apply for rather
than receive,
I would say apply for, since application
is really the burden
on public works in terms of
what we're talking about streamlining the process.
In sentence number three, it's kind of muddled.
I was just rephrasing it.
The Board discussed several ideas,
and Commissioners are open to how other towns are managing the same issue.
Agent Wagner presented
examples from Mansfield and Ledyard,
and we'll look for further information,
and the Board will continue the conversation with Jay Tullow and Joe Wagner at future meetings.
Again, something along those lines to
improve the grammar and syntax.
And as I say, I will
submitI'll send an email
and
make it easier to get that stuff
into the corrections.
Oh, and on item number 9B,
I thought we should mention
the amount
that we
requested for our budget,
so that sentence could read: The Board reviewed a budget request of $19.65
dollars for FY 'twenty three-'twenty four per estimates provided by town administrator Eric Anderson.
And following that, we approved
that request.
Okay,
so, with those
editorial
corrections,
modifications,
I'll ask,
for a motion to approve the minutes.
>> I'll make a motion to approve the minutes as amended.
>> Okay, and a second?
I'll second the amendment. Okay, second by here, Commissioner Manski.
Okay, again, I guess we'll have to do this by roll call.
Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
Commissioner Maskey?
>> Commissioner
Munro?
Aye.
And I also vote aye, so the motion carries four-zero.
Moving on, we have a window of opportunity for public comment.
But since there are no
issues for comment on the agenda,
we can, I think, move then towell,
first of all, there's no
old business
that I'm aware of?
Under new business, we had a permit application,
our first
of the year twenty
'23,
from
Jay Tuttle of the Town of Andover Public Works Department.
Essentially,
as noted in the agenda,
Mr. Tuttle is applying
for a
five year duration
permit that would generally cover
their routine
maintenance
activities
in the towns right of way, since some of those are
adjacent to or in wetlands,
they are
subject to the Commission's purview,
and we have in the past year or so
reviewed
two or three applications
from DPW,
some of which might be routine, some of which might be not so routine.
So,
we of course discussed this at the last meeting,
as noted in the minutes,
and so I'll just ask,
first off,
ask Mr. Suttle to address
the
application
and what
kinds of
things he's looking to do and how that has
progressed, I should say, from our discussion.
So, take it away. All right. Thanks, George.
>> Good evening, everybody. I'm assuming
everything got to you and you were able to review, you know, the permit and then our
proposal,
our draft
along with that application
for
the,
you know, the type of use that this permit would cover.
Indeed, that would be nature that they did.
So, I mean, do you want me to go over that? The purpose of If you wanna just give a a quick review of
Okay. So that looking to do here.
>> All right.
So the purpose of the application,
we'd like to cover all routine drainage maintenance activities by our department.
And, you know, just a summary of that
includes routine maintenance
that we perform
throughout the town
on existing watercourses,
drainage pipes, inlets and outlets,
brush and sediment removal,
detention basin repairs or replacement,
and general roadway repairs.
And
kind of an explanation of the activity
is to cover routine maintenance
on our drainage systems.
These activities,
we were not looking to change the purpose and or flow characteristics
of the original intended use
and would restore the affected drainage system to its original condition.
Some of our typical maintenance activities
that would be covered under the permit,
Brush, again, brush removal in swales, ditches, watercourses
in and around drainage culverts where normal flow has been obstructed
by overgrown vegetation.
Sediment removal in swales.
Ditches and watercourses in and around drainage culverts where normal flow has been obstructed by eroded upland soils,
stabilization
of slopes, embankments, inlets and outlets where soil or stone has eroded near the drainage system.
Tree removal within the watercourse
in around structures where it's determined that the trees and its root systems may have a negative impact that may create a hazardous
said structure.
Consultation with the tree warden will take place prior to any removals.
You know, we'd have to, if there's major tree removals,
tag them, identify them.
Repair or replacement of defective drainage structures
and or systems to include catch basins, culverts,
and or wing walls at inlets or outlets,
and any drainage pipes in the same location.
If any activity takes place within a roadway, the disturbed roadway would be repaired
and repaved.
And any prior any activities, we'd notify the wetlands agent,
you know, give them a heads up, hey, we're planning on doing some work on such and such a location and
such and such time.
And, you know, try not to have things that they're a surprise.
If things come up where
we're looking to make improvements to a system, well, yeah, that's where we gotta do a. We gotta come to you and seek individual
applications
for that if we're changing something
to those areas.
>> Okay,
thanks for that overview,
and
I'll ask
the commissioners if they have any questions
or comments
regarding this
application
for a basically five year permit
for the activities, as Mr. Tuttle has just described.
Mr. Larson?
>> Well, I do have several,
but
so
I guess
my bottom line
would be I think the last
bullet under the
typical maintenance things, repair or replacement of defective drainage structures,
all that stuff,
I think that might be a step too far
for
me anyhow.
The
but
going back,
Jay, would you expect to be briefing
the Wetlands agent on,
you know, brush removal and, you know, the first
couple of bullets in there were, it sounds like pretty routine maintenance. And I don't know that, you know, that's not what you guys are doing every week. And I don't know that
that would be something that you would go over to brief Joe on before you get started in that. That'd be just something you go off and do, isn't it?
>> Yeah, well, you know,
for instance,
couple weeks ago prior to this little cold snap, you know, we we were scraping the edges of the road, you know, removing leaves and whatnot.
And,
you know, that's
something we do all the time. You got leaves piled up on the edge of the road, we got to take care of it.
But the thing is, is
what I'm
trying to understand through the whole process and what you guys are looking for,
if I make a general notification
to Joe or whoever the Inland Wetlands agent is,
you know, we go out like Hendy Road, for instance, we did some work on it last year.
We, I'd like to go back and at least we're talking about
doing some drainage there, but we can pick away at certain areas where the brush is,
just go in along the ditch lines and clean that stuff. We're roadside mower, that's a general thing. But if we're removing trees,
and if we're starting to reshape the ditches at these inlets and outlets,
well that's some notification at least he should be aware of. And we say, hey Joe, we're going be doing some work,
you know, may not be tomorrow, but expect it within the next, you know, month or so.
You know, try to let them know when things are happening and what is going to be happening, because if somebody gets a phone call, you know, knows about it.
And you know, just trying to
make the communication process a little better, I guess,
of these routine things.
And as
>> far as you're concerned on the last
bullet, the repair or placement of defective drainage structures in their systems,
I mean, could
could name some areas that we have failing catch basins and the pipes that go that go along with them to another catch basin,
you know, that eventually they'll have to be
repaired
or replaced.
And
is that
is that routine maintenance,
would that be covered under this or is that become a special application
process? I mean, I see
existing drainage
that for my intents and purposes,
see it as stuff that infrastructure,
if it's failed, it needs to be replaced.
You're
improving it with a better material but you're not changing the system.
You're replacing the system that's already existing.
So that's kind of what
>> I agree with everything
you said, Jay. But I'll go back to the start. I think we need to have defined,
there are things that you can do without talking to Joe.
There are some things you can do after you talk to Joe. And then Joe's going to brief us at the next meeting, at least that's what he said.
Then there's some things need the commission's
approval on.
And then there are some things that need a public hearing.
And then there are some things that need the Army Corps of Engineers review.
And I'm not smart enough to know what the wicket is for that Army Corps of Engineers review.
But I remember once upon a time,
and I think it's because we were doing a temporary repair to Hutchinson Road,
the culverts out there that we're going to do something on.
And when I was talking to Eric about that, you know, talked about before we would actually do the culvert replacement,
it would that would take an Army Corps of Engineers
review on the project because
it's got so much water flowing through the culverts all the time and
the actions we would take. And so
I'm
trying to,
if we were to say that we could go
replace the culverts
on Hutchinson Road
without
getting
the commission involved,
but we would need the Army Corps of Engineers to come in and provide oversight to it.
I don't think that's right. I think we have
an obligation to provide
our oversight before we get the Army Corps of Engineers in to take a vote on it.
Never had one of those things that we needed that degree of oversight,
but but that's
what I
was looking at.
>> Yeah, well, so,
you know, to that,
I completely
understand,
you know,
know, there's structures that have already been in place
that
were approved,
and
if you're replacing it in like kind,
you know, a pipe in the ground,
I'm getting away from myself here a little bit.
We're talking about Hutchinson Road, it's another animal because your water comes
from
different locations.
It's not drainage that follows along the roadway,
you know,
just for instance, Old Farms Road,
I can go down that road and look at every basin and every big basin needs some work or replacement.
You know, we did some work just to kind of patch it up and keep things at bay, but someday someday that's a road that's going to need some work.
That system was designed,
put in place,
approved.
It's just, you know, it's aging out.
Not looking to change it,
just got to it's got to be replaced. You're not changing the
type or size
of the flow.
Once you start increasing pipes and adding something here and there,
know, then you have a, you run
into another
animal all in itself.
If you're just adding a catch basin somewhere in between because you happen to have a long distance in between two catch basins, the pipes you're just trying to, you know, collect that water in a certain area that's not really changing it, you're not changing the size of the pipe, you're just adding a collection area in between two
basins.
But yeah, there are things that Joe will definitely have to be aware of,
and there are things that the Commission definitely needs to be aware of and and go through the the proper.
You know, proper process, I'm looking
at more of the routine activities,
the day to day things that we do.
>> I know you are. That's the purpose of this. Can I add something, if you don't mind? I was just looking
at that last
bullet point, it says repair or replacement of defective drainage structures
in our system. So that's different.
Being a drainage structure would be different than,
like, a culvert that house a brook or water course in there, which would need
commission approval. So these would cut this this permit would cover the drainage structures, like stuff that goes on a road that would carry storm water, things like that.
>> Well, that bullet does say to include catch basins, culverts,
end of wing walls
at inlands and outlets,
and any drainage pipes in the same location.
And and so that was,
you know, my concern. There's some pretty big culverts
in
and we've had essentially,
you know, one permit a year over the last three years, if you would, that,
you know, we've we've
discussed a public works
item.
And I don't think
that has
overtaxed
the Inland Wetlands Commission in dealing with those.
And in fact, you know, I felt that it's
been
beneficial to my knowledge and understanding of
wetlands things having
gone through the permitting process. Now that's putting, you know, that's not in Jay's job description to train the Inland Wetlands Commission up on how things go.
But I do think that we would be able to provide a different perspective than what Jay's
working at.
It might be able to add value to the discussion when we're coming up with a plan.
Another one, you know,
I'm very aware of as I walk around the lake every day is
Basola Rogue
Culvert or whatever, where the wing wall is,
you know, falling apart over there.
And I don't see our role as deciding whether or not we can do the job.
You know, if
the road is collapsing, we have to fix it.
Hopefully we're adding value to how to do it in the most environmentally
conscious
way.
And
so that's
my thought on that.
Don't know if Jay feels we have
overtaxed the public works department by coming
a year, but I thought the
opportunities we've had to interact on those things was
beneficial. I think, you know, the public hearing we had on the
shotty mill thing,
although the pertinent comments weren't
to what we had done last year, but for a future plan,
you know, I thought the input we got from the public was very valuable there too. And I think that probably would come into,
you know, requiring a commission permit. But I just think that that bullet, the last one there, the way it's worded probably
precludes the commission from from having a say in those things that we might need to have a say in.
>> What if we limited it to
up to 24 inches
culvert, you know, 20
pipes
culverts
that
and their end you know end or wing walls you know that that's small
that's our daily routine
maintenance things I can I can think of several 24 inches well there's a couple on handy that that need to be done? There's some CMP,
old
metal pipe that needs to be replaced, Culver going across the road,
and
there
is no more wing wall or
the head wall is starting to fall over because the road has been widened so many times over the years and traffic just keeps pushing the wall.
And we've done that in
several areas. So if we limit to
size,
then your concerns of, yeah, I wouldn't do anything with Basola Road
without
any type of plan or approval. I mean, I'd be crazy to do something like that. Not that I wouldn't do it, try.
>> Well, then, know, way I read the, you know, that item on there,
it seems like, you know, we would be giving you authority to do that. Yeah, I see your point.
I do.
>> Comments from other commissioners or from Agent Wagner? I have a couple of ideas, but I want to give others first chance.
No, go ahead.
>> I'm thinking that one differentiation
we can apply here is a natural water course. For example, Missoula Road,
that, you know, is a natural
and
more or less continuous
water course,
likewise,
as mentioned on Hutchinson Road. As I recall too, when we looked at the application,
and there
was no specific application for that, but we were talking with Eric Anderson on the
Hutchinson Road situation.
And Jed, I think that's where the comment about the
Army Corps coming in.
Again, that's a natural and persistent
water course
that
that collapsed
culvert or collapsing culvert
is channeling,
and that's why it required
the Army Corps because there's
a possibility, I guess, of fish going upstream
from, I guess, connects down the Hawk River. So, you know, as part of a system,
natural and, as I say, persistent water system. So, that's the one distinction that we can make
that would again
specify
a condition where a permit application would definitely be required.
Okay,
the idea of size of cover is, again, that might cover the same base, but it would,
in most cases, but as you say in terms of
wetlands conditions,
talking about a persistent or, you know,
year
round water course
as opposed to an intermittent water course or a drainage feature,
would
indicate
where a permit application
was required.
And thinking back again, as
Commissioner Larson pointed out, we had a
permit application and even a hearing
for the work that was recently done on Shawty Mill Road,
where basically
there was some redirection
of water courses
as well as
the kind of routine maintenance that
Ms. Tuttle has referred to.
But, you know, further up
the hill
we also recently had
application and we approved a permit for
a drainage pipe replacement
at the corner of Wales Road
andor on Schottie Mill
at
Wales Road. There was a section of pipe that was in an upland review area that is adjacent to a wetland that needed to be replaced.
It seems to me that, you know, under the proposal
that
particular
action, that particular
repair
might not have needed
a
permit.
We issued a permit for it, but it seems to me that under
the conditions
that we're discussing now
that wouldn't have been necessary.
On the other hand,
the permit
application for the work on Lower Shawty Mill Road down past Birch Road or Birch Drive would have still require, will still, such work would still require a permit.
Does that
make sense?
>> We That does make sense, and I know,
you know, probably since that
upper pipe in Jay was that a 24 inches pipe up there on
Shotty Mill in
Wales?
No,
was 15 inches. Okay, so
>> that is within your 24 and I think
you know, now
a permit wouldn't come to the commission
in the Upland Review area anyhow.
Agent Wagner would
process that
on his own. So if that application
were coming today, I don't know that it would come to the Commission
anyhow because it's not in a wetland
going on what you said that's in the Upland Review Area.
So Greg?
Yep.
>> Again, I I in my view, I wouldn't even need a permit request.
Obviously, communication,
with agent Wagner or the wetlands agent,
but not necessarily a formal application.
>> Right, that would have been one where
it's
right on the side of the road,
it's near a wetland, but we're replacing the pipe with like kind and replacing the structures. Yeah,
>> well, would be covered under the general permit. Under this, correct.
Yeah. Yep.
>> Okay.
So,
the real key here and what we need to think about, you know, we're not going towe have to, of course, wait until the next meeting
before we can vote on this
permit application.
So, I think we will have some time to consider
how
wewhere
do we make that cut? How do we make it clear
to
commissioners
and public works alike
what
cutoff
point is? And
I'm thinking that, again, a little bit of language and also a little bit of
communication between
public works and the wetland agent,
I think that
our wetland agent
is perfectly capable of saying, Nah, you better get a permit for that one.
You better run this by, you know, we better get to run a specific
permit
application by the Commission for this one,
as opposed to now this is something that clearly
you can do under the general permit.
I
think again we can probably look
to make some
small modifications in the language of the permit application,
the general permit application you're looking for,
But we're certainly, I think, in agreement that this is a good way to go and as
an approach to
basically mitigating the amount of work that is required on the part of public works to get the work done,
this five year permit approach
is probably
better
than
the other approaches that we discussed, namely
amending our regulations
or
simply working on a kind of
memorandum of understanding.
If you recall the last meeting, we talked about
the
Mansfield
example,
which was basically just a memorandum of understanding,
and the ledger example,
which was
a specific
item in the regulations
to allow for certain activities.
It seems to me that amending regulations
is typically cumbersome
and
even harder to get right
than what we are looking at now,
and that the memorandum of understanding
depends on having an understanding.
And as
personnel change, then understandings
can change.
So,
I like, I really do like the idea of
issuing a permit
because that satisfies our regulatory requirement. You know, we're doing our job
by
giving you that permit,
and Agent Wagner is doing his job
by,
as it were, enforcing
the permit requirements
and communicating
with public works about that.
And
public works is doing its job
and
being mindful
of the need to
adhere to wetlands regulations.
So, it keeps everybody on board,
and it's subject to renewal.
You know, it's a five year permit, and we can see, okay, hey, this isn't working out so well,
or
can
perhaps modify the permit next time around.
So, I think it gives us both flexibility
and
maintains enforcement
of regulations.
Agreed.
>> I got two other comments, George. Sure. Go ahead.
And would we want to consider,
you know, for the first go through,
because we haven't done this,
make it a two or three year permit with the
opportunity to provide sooner
any process improvements that we discover along the way.
Five years is a long time when this is, the first shot at something.
>> Okay,
I guess we could,
kind of take a straw poll on that.
Any other Commissioners want to, weigh in on that?
>> I I would I would I
think yeah, it's Bill Monroe. I think that Jed has a good point there. I mean, if it's being the first
of a a first of
five years is kind of a long time,
especially if it's not working out, but we could modify it anyway, couldn't we?
Or would once you have the permit, that's it.
That's the end. It's some gross violation.
Yeah.
We wouldn't be looking to rescind a permit.
Rescind.
Okay.
>> And my last comment would be in the agenda for tonight, it talks about
specifying that this is all work that would be done in the town right away.
And I didn't see that in the draft
Permit.
>> Yeah, well,
didn't specify
that
to limit the town's right of way
because the town has a right to drain. So, I got to go in an extra 10 feet
beyond the actual right of way, call it just for,
you know, sake of conversation 15 feet from the edge of the road,
but that ditch,
you know, or that
goes out into the
wood line a little bit and there's a pile of leaves or a tree that's linked because I can, I see them in my head, you know, there's a tree laying down, I gotta reach in a little bit further?
So, you know, that's, that's, yes,
most everything is,
call it 90%,
85% of the time. It's all on the within the towns right away within the It's
just those occasional
areas. Gotta give it a little more shape.
I understand. Especially if there's Question the inconsistency
there. Yeah, especially when there's sediment buildup. If there's so much sediment that's been going on to somebody's property,
know, like to take that back out of there, you know, and clean it up.
Part of restoration.
And again, if it's a spot where
it's questionable
or,
you know,
I'm doing a little bit more than I should have, I gotta make a phone call. I'm gonna call Joe or notify you guys and
you know, it's kind of there's a,
you know, there is a fine line. It's just hard to define that. It is. I I hate to say common sense applies, and I understand that sometimes,
you know, common sense goes out the window, but I try not to do that.
I know you do.
>> The thing I'm I just like I wanted
to provide the draft permit
just so you guys could see because it's slightly different. You know, having a general permit that covers all these activities is kind of different than
the normal stuff that we do.
So I thought I would write this permit so you guys could review it and make sure because this would be like what,
you know, the finished product.
So
put it on paper, and you guys can you know, if you you wanna change the wording or anything.
But we could kinda get a feel for how it's gonna look when it was done. That's just why I put it on there.
Yep.
>> Chairman Elliott, do have one question about this I'm
wondering about, like,
big trees or
trees
that are need to be cut cut down
because they're in one way or another causing
a jam up.
How does this fit into what you're trying to do right here trying to streamline
this
permit process? You know, if there's a big tree on somebody's property that's like right on the edge, half on their property, half on right away.
>> That's,
that's where the
Yeah, that's where I got to come in as a town warden, tree warden,
I have to notify
property owners.
I have to tag the tree for so,
you know, for so many days, notify the public.
And, you know, we're not just talking to, you know, four inch scrub brush tree. You know we're talking some something substantial.
Typically around structures and again I'm going to refer back to
the Hendy Road bridge over the Hop River.
So,
and there's other structures
and
you know, go back to our head walls of our bigger
head walls.
You know,
typically
you try not to have things within 25
feet
of a structure.
That's kind of the rule of thumb.
You
know, and that's more.
That's more like something's major
dams,
you know,
and
because you don't want those root systems getting in and you
know disturbing those soils and eventually putting pressure on those those walls.
So, I try to
keep
vegetation away from wing walls, abutments, and things like that.
We have a lot of stone structures,
stone abutments.
So, if you get something in there and the tree, you know, starts
to look like it's failing or it's leaning over a little bit more, that's putting pressure on those,
you know, stone abutments. So yeah, I do look to clear those
trees and get them away from there just so we can preserve
those structures.
But again, I have to
notify
property owners and that's
mandated. That's
state statute.
Okay.
That's the state's something
>> that is like there's a tree under the bridge right now at Handy that creeps out, starts to grow from
peaks its ugly head out on the side. I really just need to go out and just take that out.
Someday when the water is low and there's you know, hardly no flow, we need to get rid of it. There's a few other trees that we just need to get out of there.
If they're, if they are a hazard, I can deem them a hazard
or a warden can deem things a hazard and it doesn't have to be,
no notification is needed.
I have to.
>> The Department of Public Works, when the Director of Public Works wants to consult with the tree warden, it's a very short conversation
there.
Oh, one other thing I'll put
on the other and
go back and forth.
>> Did have one other thing. I was a little just unclear of as far as, like, what if you have to build something on somebody's property, like, in your job?
I mean, like, whatever it is. It's,
you know, like,
what do you how do you go about that? So
>> I'll refer back to
Shotting Mill Road last year.
You know, the the town has
some easements
here and there drainage easements that have been made, know, like the new developments have some formal easements that were
made during the
process of their construction and planning.
But for Shotty Mill Road, those drainage areas,
I actually approached the property owners of the individual
spots and I
did temporary easements with them, drafted a temporary easement that gave
the town of Andover permission to encroach on their land
to do a specific
task.
And it was spelled out for them and discussed
quite a few times
back and forth. I addressed their concerns and our concerns. And ultimately,
that's
what we came away with. Now we have,
you know, like at 34 with that stone
water courses on the edge of the road, it's mostly in our right away, but it's still a little bit in the property owners link right away, you know, we can maintain it
from our
side.
But if we have to do something major in there, there's, you know, we have a temporary easement for a year,
and then it reverts back. So anytime that we've got to do something major, if we got to encroach on their property again, we'll have to, you know, talk to them again.
So there's there's there's some limitations that I can do,
you know, in the way of temporary easements.
We're doing formal easements,
something that's going to be on record permanently, then we gotta, you know, seek
town attorney and you know, just get some private. I mean, the proper wording and everything. Everybody's all on board.
Okay.
>> So, it's like if you have something on your property, I need to get on to your land, run my piece of equipment or our piece of equipment over there. I draft a
temporary easement
permission
and I've got to go and do what I got to do and repair everything on my way out
as good if not better than before.
That's what I try to do.
Oh, okay.
If that makes sense.
Yes.
>> Okay. So do we have any, further,
comments?
Mr. Larson, did you
get to the end of your list?
I think I got enough.
Okay.
Christian Maski.
I'm good.
Okay. Christian Monroe?
Good.
>> Okay.
Then,
okay. So, we'll take under advisement, and I think that, again,
some communication
between
Mr. Tuttle
and Agent Wagner
regarding the potential
to modify
the permit
application
prior to our next meeting,
when we will be able to
take action
on that application.
So it seems to me, again, to summarize,
the
two
main issues are the
upper
bound
for what kind of activities
would
be included
in this blanket
permit.
You know, at what point does it become something that has to come before the Commission,
and then the duration
of this initial
permit, whether two
or three years
as opposed to five,
okay?
So, we'll look forward to seeing this on our agenda next month
and hope to be able to take action
and
again
do what we can to expedite
the process
for getting the work done.
So,
with that, I think we can move on
to our next item in the agenda.
Again, if anybody has any, further thoughts after the meeting, be sure and try and communicate them to Agent Wagner so he can relay
them to
Mr. Tuttle so that we can again make sure that we have everything covered,
before we look at the application again,
next,
next month.
Okay?
Again, thanks for your time, Jay. You can excuse yourself from the meeting now, and we'll head on to our next item of business.
>> Alright. Thank you much. Have a good evening. You're welcome. Yeah.
>> Okay.
Next we have our agent reports.
So agent Wagner.
>> And then one,
extension of the permit duration for the 25 Sider Mill Road that was a,
like, a temporary stream crossing
that they they
were using to con construct a French drain along their
foundation.
And
I guess they haven't finished the French drain yet, so
they asked for an extension. But since that new public act
21 dash 34
came about,
the permits
were automatically extended. So
I just
made a note of that in the town file, and
it'll be extended
for
it was a long time. I forget exactly, but it was another fourteen years maybe.
So
Oh my goodness. Well,
>> good. It's good that the Public
Act 2134
allows you to do that because I
didn't realize it was that long.
Yeah.
>> Whoever lobbied for that change wanted to make sure that they had a lot of leeway.
Questions about that or,
again, I don't recall,
that was something
we approved. We went on a sidewalk,
we checked it out, and the whole contingency of being able to cross Stallbrook
without having to
construct a bridge or even, you know, they're hoping I think for
dry enough conditions just to be able to.
Take a vehicle over the stream bed without any kind of.
Bridging.
>> Yeah, I believe that's what they did this summer because it was so wild that that they could just drive across without having to do anything.
>> Right, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, that was then we've had substantial
water since then. Don't think you can get across that. I'll book it in water.
Yeah. Yeah.
Well, then
want to item agenda item number nine, other business commission vacancies.
As you all know, we've got a lot, and I'm pleased to see
that we have a prospective
member of the commission, a volunteer,
Mr. Duncan Fife,
who's on the call
identifying
Yeah, right, your name is there. Okay, good. So, you all can see him, and
I'd like to ask you
just to speak to your interest
in serving on the Commission and a little bit about your background and,
you know, what you think you can bring to the table so to speak.
>> Sure, so
good evening. My name is Duncan. I actually moved to town about a year ago.
I saw the post for the vacancies
online so I always had a passion for environmental sustainability.
That's why I went to college where I graduated from Yukon
with a degree in agriculture natural resources.
I also worked for the town of Windsor for DPW also.
So it's good to kinda see both sides, you know, just like we're listening to Jay talk about what he does with the head walls and basins
and whatever else. But, yeah, I think it'd be great to join the team and,
you know, help out and,
you know, be part of the town of Andover.
>> I
think we all appreciate the need for
civic involvement,
and it's good to see somebody too that's
maybe not quite a retiree like most of this.
I don't know that gray hair and gray beard are actually required for this kind of division. Obviously not.
It
seems some time to go with the turf. Most of our commissions arewhat
is this? Some kind of a gerontocracy
perhaps
in terms of town governments.
So,
okay, well, we'll take it then that
we heard your expression of interest and background.
So, I think we would be in a position to
recommend
your appointment
to the Board of Selectmen. I think that, Duncan, I think that Adj. Wagner
gave you the drill on what
the bylaws in the charter
specify,
namely that
we serve two year terms.
You would be appointed for a partial term
that
would end
in
June, at the end of June. But appointment
is pretty much automatic.
Reappointment is automatic
unless you say, I don't want to do it anymore,
you will be reappointed
ad infinitum.
We, you
know, under the Charter, we
can fill an interim vacancy
on our own
recognizance.
And
as they say, we will recommend
your appointment
then to the Board of Selectmen, which will make the official
appointment.
We can act on that, in fact, tonight,
and I would move
then that the Commission
appoint
Mr. Dunning Fife
as a
regular member of the commission. There is a regular vacancy
beginning,
well, with our next meeting
in March,
and again, turn
to run
through
the end of twenty twenty three.
So, that's the motion. I'll ask for a second.
I enthusiastically
second the motion.
>> Okay,
Commissioner Larson,
and again, roll call vote. Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
Commissioner Mashke?
Commissioner Monroe?
Aye.
And
>> aye, Chairman Elliott, also enthusiastically
vote yes for the appointment,
and we will again communicate that to the Board of Selectmen. We look forward to having you participate
in our next meeting. And you've already gotten a good background by sitting in on this meeting because we know that the first item on the agenda
at our next meeting will be the
request
from Department of Public Works.
You already had a good background on that.
I
think that, again, Agent Wagner pointed out to the opportunities for training the
Department of Energy and Environmental Protection
website
with
the course that's administered through UConn
Extension,
a very valuable
introduction to wetlands and wetland regulations.
I had a background in soil science,
but I learned a good bit about
that, and I even learned that what we used to call models are now oxy reductive features. So, hey,
something new for everyone in that course.
So, I encourage you to take a look at that, of course, the regulations
and the bylaws
so that you can familiarize
yourself
with the activities and the way we do business.
So, again, look forward to seeing you
at our subsequent meeting.
>> Thank you. I appreciate it. I look forward to working with everyone.
>> Glad the opportunity was here for you.
Okay,
well, our next regular meeting on the agenda is Monday, March 6, so again, pm, again on Zoom.
And with that,
I will entertain a motion for adjournment.
Motion will you adjourn?
Seconded.
>> Okay, motion is seconded.
All in favor, just push the little leave button on there, right?
Will say,
yeah, already, say bye. Good night, everybody.
You're Good welcome, Duncan. Thanks for being here, and, we'll look forward to seeing you.
And
once again, I'll be in touch
by email about corrections to the previous minutes. So,
thanks all, and have a good evening, and see you in a month.
Good night.
Bye.